Carl Lovelace papers, Inclusive: 1865-1969, undated, Bulk: 1900-1944
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Carl Lovelace papers
Inclusive: 1865-1969, undated, Bulk: 1900-1944
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
13
Lovelace, Carl
3 document boxes
The Carl Lovelace papers consist of correspondence, literary productions, photographic materials, and other documents relating to Dr. Lovelace's life as a Rough Rider, doctor, and Baylor Alumnus.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Carl Lovelace was born in Jefferson City, Missouri on1876 February 6, to Sarah Harrison and Major Thomas Jefferson Lovelace. The family settled in Waco in 1889, and Carl attended Baylor University. During his time at Baylor, Carl was part of the Erisophian Literary Society, and editor-in-chief of the Baylor Literary. In addition, Carl was one of the original students to kidnap W.C. Brann and bring him to the Baylor campus in 1897, but Lovelace had no part of the violent confrontation that eventually ended Brann’s life.
At the start of the Spanish-American War, Lovelace graduated from Baylor early in order to join Teddy Roosevelt’s Rough Riders military unit. As a member of the First Volunteer Calvary, Troop D, he was the only known Baylor student to participate in combat during that war. He took part in the Battle of Kettle Hill, and witnessed the charge up San Juan Hill, an experience that was foundational to his later identity and political opinions.
After returning from the war, Carl went to Vanderbilt Medical School from 1899-1900, and eventually earned his MD from Columbian University (now George Washington University) in 1902. Soon thereafter, Carl Lovelace embarked on another adventure, this time in South America. He became the chief surgeon of the Madeira-Mamoré Railroad construction project in Bolivia. That project would become notorious for more than 1,000 casualties, but Lovelace was well-respected for fighting the rampant contagious diseases and preventing even more deaths.
Back in the United States, Carl married Lucille Hill in 1915 and the two had three sons. He served as a Major in the Army Medical Corps during World War I, and eventually became a family doctor and the Medical Director for Amicable Life Insurance Company in Waco from 1919 until close to his death. He also remained an active member of the Baylor community, serving as the Baylor Alumni Association President in 1915. Carl Lovelace died on 1944 September 14, while two of his sons were fighting in World War II and his third son was a student at Baylor University.
Scope and Content
The Carl Lovelace papers consists of correspondence, legal documents, financial records, literary productions, and photographic materials collected and produced by Dr. Carl Lovelace. Documents contained in this collection include those pertaining to his time at Baylor University, his experience as a Rough Rider, his work in South America, and his life as a prominent doctor in Waco after his return to the United States.
Dr. Carl Lovelace was part of many notable historical moments during his lifetime, including the Waco, Texas, W.C. Brann Incident, Teddy Roosevelt’s Rough Riders, the Madeira-Mamoré Railroad construction project, and World War I. The Carl Lovelace papers provide a fascinating look into Texas, American, and world history at the turn of the 20th century.
Arrangement
Prior to this finding aid, the Carl Lovelace papers were roughly arranged in folders topically and by material type, but there was no overall organizational system and no series. Whenever possible, these categories have been maintained as folder titles.
Currently, the papers are arranged into five series: I: Correspondence, II: Legal Documents, III: Financial Records, IV: Literary Productions, and V: Photographic Materials.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 13. Acquired 0-00-00
Related Resources
Related references
A.J. Peeler & Co. The Standard Blue Book. Texas ed. San Antonio: A.J. Peeler & Co, 1920, 200.
Baylor Alumni Association. “History of BAA.” Baylor Alumni Association. Accessed 2013 September 17.
Black, Andrew Donald. “Student Vigilante, Rough Rider, and Physician: The Life of Dr. Carl Lovelace.” Honors Thesis, Baylor University, 1997.
“Resurrecting the Devil’s Railway in Brazil.” 2010. BBC, November 27, sec. Latin America & Caribbean. Accessed 2020 May 6.
Roosevelt, Theodore. The Rough Riders. New York: C. Scribner’s Sons, 1899.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Brann, William Cowper, 1855-1898.
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- Alumni and alumnae.; Baylor University. Erisophian Literary Society.
Subjects
Physicians -- Texas.; Railroads -- Bolivia.; Spanish-American War, 1898.
Genres
Correspondence.; Essays.; Financial records.; Legal documents.; Photographs.
- Correspondence, 1903-1959, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series consists of personal correspondence and correspondence related to Baylor, the Madeira-Mamoré Association, the Brazil Railroad, and Dr. Lovelace's medical career. This series is in average to good condition.
  - Personal Correspondence, 1903-1918 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1921-1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1943-1959 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Baylor Correspondence, 1891-1927 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Baylor Correspondence, 1928-1932 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Baylor Correspondence, 1933-1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Medical Correspondence, 1917-1925 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Medical Correspondence, 1928-1943 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Madeira-Mamoré Association Correspondence, 1929-1938 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Madeira-Mamoré Association Correspondence, 1939-1940 March (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Madeira-Mamoré Association Correspondence, 1940 June-1942 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Brazil Railway Correspondence, 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Brazil Railway Correspondence, 1930-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Legal Documents, 1914; 2
  This series contains legal documents pertaining to Carl Lovelace. This series is in good condition.
  - Legal Documents, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Financial Records, 1865-1920; 3
  General condition: Average.
  This series contains financial receipts and other financial materials relating to Carl Lovelace. This series is in average condition.
  - Financial Receipts, 1897-1920 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - General, 1865-1918 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Literary Productions, 1873-1969, undated; 4
  This series contains a wide variety of literary productions collected and produced by Carl Lovelace. They include documents pertaining to his medical career, his participation in the Waco Philosophers Club, and many other aspects of his life. This series is in good condition.
  - Medical Records and Receipts, 1917, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Medical Essays, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Medical Publications, 1912-1916 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Medical Publications, 1917-1918, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Medical Publications, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Philosophers Club: Membership Lists and Schedules, 1936-1943 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Philosophers Club: Circular Letters, 1930-1944 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Philosophers Club: Essays (1 of 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Philosophers Club: Essays (2 of 2), undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Madeira-Mamoré Association: Newsletters, 1937-1939 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Baylor Literary Productions, 1873-1936 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - General: Essays, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - General: Autograph Book, 1895-1896 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - General: Poetry, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - General: Humor, 1952-1969, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - General, 1894, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Photographic Materials, circa 1905, undated; 5
  This series contains photographs of Carl Lovelace and his family. It also contains photographs identified simply as "American Hospital" that appear to depict his work with the Madeira-Mamoré Association in South America. This series is in good condition.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Photographic print
  - "American Hospital", circa 1905 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Lovelace Family, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)